hey everyone welcome back to this Tosca
automation playlist and today we are
going to talk about how you can handle
different date expressions in Tosca
now in your application you can come
across different scenarios where you may
need to enter some date maybe it is the
current date or maybe you need to do
some calculations based on some uh
months or days you have to add them or
sub or you have to remove them right so
there are several types of date related
scenarios which comes up whenever we try
to automate some application
so generally in other automation tools
you need to write something either on
Java or dotnet to get these dates right
which may be a customized it or maybe
the current system date or something
like that
but in Tosca uh already the t-box
modules are present okay and the date
expressions are also present through
which you can easily get the system date
or any other date format which you want
and you want to enter them into your
application so you can use this
Expressions to basically format your
dates and
use it according to your application so
let's see at some of the examples
so I have prepared this test case which
basically gets all the different types
of dates and also days and times and all
the other things right so I have
completely used uh the Expressions the
data Expressions which are available in
Tosca
so for this I've just used a t-box set
buffer module and then for now I'm just
setting the buffer to all of these
different uh dates okay date types
so let's go through each of them keep in
mind that there are more Expressions I
have just used some of them but um you
can go ahead and explore all the
different types of expressions and see
which one fits your requirements okay
uh also to write this Expressions well
it's very simple you just type the curly
Breeze and then you will see the list of
different expressions are available and
out of that some of them are related to
the date types okay so for this I've
used something like the date okay and in
the description you can see it Returns
the full current date
okay and the date and time values can be
calculated also using the base State
along with deviations and this we will
see in a later example okay
so this will basically return me the
current full date okay
and then if you want to have the
timestamp then you can use the date time
expression if you just want the time
then you can use the time expression
similarly if you want the current day or
current month or current year okay then
you can use this respective Expressions
which is day month and year
now sometimes it happens that you would
require the first day of the month or
the last day of the month for that also
there is an expression called month
first and month last
and then there are some specific uh date
requirements which you need to fulfill
like the system date okay so this will
return the full date uh based on your
system specification so like the date is
defined in your system the date format
it will display the same date here okay
then um if you want uh the days the
month or year uh in a specific format
like uh in a two digits format right so
even if there is just one digit in the D
then it is going to add a zero okay it
will prefix a zero into that to make it
two digits so if you want all these uh
day month and year in two digits you can
use this Expressions which is end day
and month and N here
similarly if you want the letters only
for the day or the month okay
so you can use this Expressions uh a d
and a month okay so this will return you
um some days like mon or month like Mar
for March right
now coming to the calculations okay so
if you want to have a date which is
based on some calculations okay
so you can use the same expression date
but along with that you can also do some
deviations right so if I want to add two
months to my current date or I want to
subtract one day from my current uh date
okay also you can pass uh the format on
which you want to get this output so if
you want in this format YY mmdd then you
have to write it uh in this particular
date expression okay
so it allows you to do deviations from
the current date and also it allows you
to change the format okay so your
expression will look like this it will
start with date
and then I have passed the full date
which is a buffer value right so which I
am capturing in the first buffer value
full date so that's my date okay and
then um this is my deviation so I have
added two months and I have subtracted
1D from this uh full date okay and then
I am returning the final date in this
particular format which is YY mmdt
so
this kind of Divisions you can do easily
which can fit your requirements for your
application okay
so let's go ahead and run this and see
what are the output values for all of
these different data Expressions okay
so now if I go uh in the scratch book
and in the log info I should have
received all the output values right so
you can see the first one full date this
is the date or current date right 14 8
then we have got the current timestamp
so it comes with uh the date and the
time right so this is like a timestamp
which you can use this is the current
time uh this is the current D okay so 14
is the day today
and then this is the current month Uh
current year all is in the numeric
format okay
and this is the first day of the month
okay so
it took the current date and then it set
the current date to the first day of the
month okay
similarly it's also set the last day of
the month
and then this is the system date so it's
in a specific format as you can see
this is uh the two digit format which I
told you about so everything is in two
digit you can see although the month
eight is just one digit okay so this is
the current month you can get it in two
digits using this particular format okay
or this expression
similarly as I said if you want the
particular output in three letters like
the day or the month you can use this
particular expression and then the
calculated date right
so our current date is you can see 14a
2023 it's in a specific format which
which we have defined plus it has added
two months okay so the month is now 10
and also it is subtracted one day from
14 it went to 13 right so this is uh the
calculated date which we got from the
expression
so you can see you can get any type of
date uh or any type of format right from
the Expressions okay and you can also do
some deviations in terms of uh changing
the date based on some particular
calculations
now let's look at the real-time
application with a very small example of
how we can use this data Expressions to
automate some scenarios in the
application
so I have opened this obstacle uh where
you have got a field a text field where
you need to enter the tomorrow State and
it should be in this particular format
which is ddmm and by by right so it's a
very simple uh Dynamic date expression
which you need to fill using the
expressions in Tosca and fill in to this
particular text field right
so let's create another test case here
and let's see get tomorrow's
date
I've already scanned this module so I'm
going to place it here
okay and you can see there is this date
field okay where we need to provide the
value
so for this what we are going to do is
we are going to use this particular
expression which is the date expression
so if you're not entering any particular
date then you need to enter the square
brackets which is empty and also if
you're not entering any particular
format then you have to keep the square
brackets and in the middle I need
tomorrow's date so I'm doing a plus 1D
okay so which will basically give me the
tomorrow's date okay
so this is uh what you need to use in
the expression for your date value
and let's go ahead and run this now okay
so it should be entering tomorrow's date
in that particular text field
okay as you can see uh the test case
passed so it was able to enter uh
tomorrow's date okay
and since the default format was DDM by
bye bye so we didn't have to change the
format so this was a very simple example
of
um where you can find these kind of
fields date fields where you need to
either enter today's date or in some
specific format or you need to do some
deviations right
so that's all for this particular video
I hope you enjoyed it and you learned
something new today if you want to watch
more videos then please subscribe to our
Channel
also if you have any questions then
please leave them in the comments so
until we meet again thank you and see
you next time